<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="juliaventurini.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="juliaventurini.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-02T08:29:21+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Julia Venturini</title><subtitle>Personal page of astrophysicist Julia Venturini</subtitle><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><entry><title type="html">From super-Earths to sub-Neptunes: Observational constraints and connections to theoretical models</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/08/01/sub-neptunes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From super-Earths to sub-Neptunes: Observational constraints and connections to theoretical models" /><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/08/01/sub-neptunes</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/08/01/sub-neptunes.html"><![CDATA[<p>The growing number of well-characterized exoplanets smaller than Neptune enables us to conduct more detailed population studies. We have updated the PlanetS catalog of transiting planets with precise and robust mass and radius measurements and use this comprehensive catalog to explore mass-radius (M-R) diagrams. On the one hand, we propose new M-R relationships to separate exoplanets into three populations: rocky planets, volatile-rich planets, and giant planets. On the other hand, we explore the transition in radius and density between super-Earths and sub-Neptunes around M-dwarfs and compare them with those orbiting K- and FG-dwarfs. Using Kernel density estimation method with a re-sampling technique, we estimated the normalized density and radius distributions, revealing connections between observations and theories on composition, internal structure, formation, and evolution of these exo-planets orbiting different spectral types. First, the substantial 30% increase in the number of well-characterized exoplanets orbiting M-dwarfs compared with previous studies shows us that there is no clear gap in either composition or radius between super-Earths and sub-Neptunes. The “water-worlds” around M-dwarfs cannot correspond to a distinct population, their bulk density and equilibrium temperature can be interpreted by several different internal structures and compositions. The continuity in the fraction of volatiles in these planets suggests a formation scenario involving planetesimal or hybrid pebble-planetesimal accretion. Moreover, we find that the transition between super-Earths and sub-Neptunes appears to happen at different masses (and radii) depending on the spectral type of the star. The maximum mass of super-Earths seems to be close to 10 M⊕ for all spectral types, but the minimum mass of sub-Neptunes increases with the star’s mass, and is around 1.9 M⊕, 3.4 M⊕, and 4.3 M⊕, for M-dwarfs, K-dwarfs, and FG-dwarfs, respectively. The precise value of this minimum mass may be affected by observational bias, but the trend appears to be reliable. This effect, attributed to planet migration, also contributes to the fading of the radius valley for M-planets compared to FGK-planets. While sub-Neptunes are less common around M-dwarfs, smaller ones (1.8 Re &lt; Rp &lt; 2.8 R⊕) exhibit lower density than their equivalents around FGK-dwarfs. Nonetheless, the sample of well-characterized small exoplanets remains limited, and each new discovery has the potential to reshape our understanding and interpretations of this population in the context of internal structure, composition, formation, and evolution models. Broader consensus is also needed for internal structure models and atmospheric compositions to enhance density interpretation and observable predictions for the atmospheres of these exoplanets.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.04311.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.04311.pdf</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="L. Parc" /><category term="F. Bouchy" /><category term="J. Venturini" /><category term="C. Dorn" /><category term="R. Helled" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The growing number of well-characterized exoplanets smaller than Neptune enables us to conduct more detailed population studies. We have updated the PlanetS catalog of transiting planets with precise and robust mass and radius measurements and use this comprehensive catalog to explore mass-radius (M-R) diagrams. On the one hand, we propose new M-R relationships to separate exoplanets into three populations: rocky planets, volatile-rich planets, and giant planets. On the other hand, we explore the transition in radius and density between super-Earths and sub-Neptunes around M-dwarfs and compare them with those orbiting K- and FG-dwarfs. Using Kernel density estimation method with a re-sampling technique, we estimated the normalized density and radius distributions, revealing connections between observations and theories on composition, internal structure, formation, and evolution of these exo-planets orbiting different spectral types. First, the substantial 30% increase in the number of well-characterized exoplanets orbiting M-dwarfs compared with previous studies shows us that there is no clear gap in either composition or radius between super-Earths and sub-Neptunes. The “water-worlds” around M-dwarfs cannot correspond to a distinct population, their bulk density and equilibrium temperature can be interpreted by several different internal structures and compositions. The continuity in the fraction of volatiles in these planets suggests a formation scenario involving planetesimal or hybrid pebble-planetesimal accretion. Moreover, we find that the transition between super-Earths and sub-Neptunes appears to happen at different masses (and radii) depending on the spectral type of the star. The maximum mass of super-Earths seems to be close to 10 M⊕ for all spectral types, but the minimum mass of sub-Neptunes increases with the star’s mass, and is around 1.9 M⊕, 3.4 M⊕, and 4.3 M⊕, for M-dwarfs, K-dwarfs, and FG-dwarfs, respectively. The precise value of this minimum mass may be affected by observational bias, but the trend appears to be reliable. This effect, attributed to planet migration, also contributes to the fading of the radius valley for M-planets compared to FGK-planets. While sub-Neptunes are less common around M-dwarfs, smaller ones (1.8 Re &lt; Rp &lt; 2.8 R⊕) exhibit lower density than their equivalents around FGK-dwarfs. Nonetheless, the sample of well-characterized small exoplanets remains limited, and each new discovery has the potential to reshape our understanding and interpretations of this population in the context of internal structure, composition, formation, and evolution models. Broader consensus is also needed for internal structure models and atmospheric compositions to enhance density interpretation and observable predictions for the atmospheres of these exoplanets.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A fading radius valley towards M dwarfs, a persistent density valley across stellar types</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/first%20author/2024/06/04/radius-valley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A fading radius valley towards M dwarfs, a persistent density valley across stellar types" /><published>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/first%20author/2024/06/04/radius-valley</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/first%20author/2024/06/04/radius-valley.html"><![CDATA[<p>The radius valley separating super-Earths from mini-Neptunes is a fundamental benchmark for theories of planet formation and evolution. Observations show that the location of the radius valley decreases with decreasing stellar mass and with increasing orbital period. Here, we build on our previous pebble-based formation model.
Combined with photoevaporation after disc dispersal, it has allowed us to unveil the radius valley as a separator between rocky and water-worlds. In this study, we expand our model for a range of stellar masses spanning from 0.1 to $1.5\, M_\odot$. We find that the location of the radius valley is well described by a power-law in stellar mass as $R_\mathrm{valley} = 1.8197\, M_\ast^{0.14(+0.02/−0.01)}$, which is in excellent agreement with observations. We also find very good agreement with the dependence of the radius valley on orbital period, both for FGK and M dwarfs.
Additionally, we note that the radius valley gets filled towards low stellar masses, particularly at $0.1–0.4\, M_\odot$, yielding a rather flat slope in $R_\mathrm{valley}$ − $P_\mathrm{orb}$. This is the result of orbital migration occurring at lower planet mass for less massive stars, which allows for low-mass water-worlds to reach the inner regions of the system, blurring the separation in mass (and size) between rocky and water worlds. Furthermore, we find that for planetary equilibrium temperatures above 400 K, the water in the volatile layer exists fully in the form of steam, puffing the planet radius up (as compared to the radii of condensed-water worlds). This produces an increase in planet radii of ∼30% at 1 M⊕ and of ∼15% at 5 M⊕ compared to condensed-water worlds. As with Sun-like stars, we find that pebble accretion leaves its imprint on the overall exoplanet population as a depletion of planets with intermediate compositions (i.e. water mass fractions of ∼0 − 20%), carving an planet-depleted diagonal band in the mass-radius (MR) diagrams. This band is better visualised when plotting the planet’s mean density in terms of an Earth-like composition. This change in coordinates causes the valley to emerge for all the stellar mass cases.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.01967">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.01967</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="First Author" /><category term="J. Venturini" /><category term="M. P. Ronco" /><category term="O. M. Guilera" /><category term="J. Haldemann" /><category term="C. Mordasini" /><category term="M. Miller Bertolami" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The radius valley separating super-Earths from mini-Neptunes is a fundamental benchmark for theories of planet formation and evolution. Observations show that the location of the radius valley decreases with decreasing stellar mass and with increasing orbital period. Here, we build on our previous pebble-based formation model. Combined with photoevaporation after disc dispersal, it has allowed us to unveil the radius valley as a separator between rocky and water-worlds. In this study, we expand our model for a range of stellar masses spanning from 0.1 to $1.5\, M_\odot$. We find that the location of the radius valley is well described by a power-law in stellar mass as $R_\mathrm{valley} = 1.8197\, M_\ast^{0.14(+0.02/−0.01)}$, which is in excellent agreement with observations. We also find very good agreement with the dependence of the radius valley on orbital period, both for FGK and M dwarfs. Additionally, we note that the radius valley gets filled towards low stellar masses, particularly at $0.1–0.4\, M_\odot$, yielding a rather flat slope in $R_\mathrm{valley}$ − $P_\mathrm{orb}$. This is the result of orbital migration occurring at lower planet mass for less massive stars, which allows for low-mass water-worlds to reach the inner regions of the system, blurring the separation in mass (and size) between rocky and water worlds. Furthermore, we find that for planetary equilibrium temperatures above 400 K, the water in the volatile layer exists fully in the form of steam, puffing the planet radius up (as compared to the radii of condensed-water worlds). This produces an increase in planet radii of ∼30% at 1 M⊕ and of ∼15% at 5 M⊕ compared to condensed-water worlds. As with Sun-like stars, we find that pebble accretion leaves its imprint on the overall exoplanet population as a depletion of planets with intermediate compositions (i.e. water mass fractions of ∼0 − 20%), carving an planet-depleted diagonal band in the mass-radius (MR) diagrams. This band is better visualised when plotting the planet’s mean density in terms of an Earth-like composition. This change in coordinates causes the valley to emerge for all the stellar mass cases.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CHEOPS observations of KELT-20 b/MASCARA-2 b: An aligned orbit and signs of variability from a reflective day side</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/29/KELT-20.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CHEOPS observations of KELT-20 b/MASCARA-2 b: An aligned orbit and signs of variability from a reflective day side" /><published>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/29/KELT-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/29/KELT-20.html"><![CDATA[<p>Context. Occultations are windows of opportunity to indirectly peek into the dayside atmosphere of exoplanets. High-precision transit events provide information on the spin-orbit alignment of exoplanets around fast-rotating hosts.
Aims: We aim to precisely measure the planetary radius and geometric albedo of the ultra-hot Jupiter (UHJ) KELT-20 b along with the spin-orbit alignment of the system.
Methods: We obtained optical high-precision transits and occultations of KELT-20 b using CHEOPS observations in conjunction with simultaneous TESS observations. We interpreted the occultation measurements together with archival infrared observations to measure the planetary geometric albedo and dayside temperatures. We further used the host star’s gravity-darkened nature to measure the system’s obliquity.
Results: We present a time-averaged precise occultation depth of 82 ± 6 ppm measured with seven CHEOPS visits and 131−7+8 from the analysis of all available TESS photometry. Using these measurements, we precisely constrain the geometric albedo of KELT-20 b to 0.26 ± 0.04 and the brightness temperature of the dayside hemisphere to 2566−80+77 K. Assuming Lambertian scattering law, we constrain the Bond albedo to 0.36−0.05+0.04 along with a minimal heat transfer to the night side (ϵ = 0.14−0.10+0.13). Furthermore, using five transit observations we provide stricter constraints of 3 9 ± 1 1 deg on the sky-projected obliquity of the system.
Conclusions: The aligned orbit of KELT-20 b is in contrast to previous CHEOPS studies that have found strongly inclined orbits for planets orbiting other A-type stars. The comparably high planetary geometric albedo of KELT-20 b corroborates a known trend of strongly irradiated planets being more reflective. Finally, we tentatively detect signs of temporal variability in the occultation depths, which might indicate variable cloud cover advecting onto the planetary day side.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.03264.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.03264.pdf</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="V. Singh" /><category term="G. Scandariato" /><category term="A. M. S. Smith" /><category term="CHEOPS Science Team (including J.Venturini)" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Context. Occultations are windows of opportunity to indirectly peek into the dayside atmosphere of exoplanets. High-precision transit events provide information on the spin-orbit alignment of exoplanets around fast-rotating hosts. Aims: We aim to precisely measure the planetary radius and geometric albedo of the ultra-hot Jupiter (UHJ) KELT-20 b along with the spin-orbit alignment of the system. Methods: We obtained optical high-precision transits and occultations of KELT-20 b using CHEOPS observations in conjunction with simultaneous TESS observations. We interpreted the occultation measurements together with archival infrared observations to measure the planetary geometric albedo and dayside temperatures. We further used the host star’s gravity-darkened nature to measure the system’s obliquity. Results: We present a time-averaged precise occultation depth of 82 ± 6 ppm measured with seven CHEOPS visits and 131−7+8 from the analysis of all available TESS photometry. Using these measurements, we precisely constrain the geometric albedo of KELT-20 b to 0.26 ± 0.04 and the brightness temperature of the dayside hemisphere to 2566−80+77 K. Assuming Lambertian scattering law, we constrain the Bond albedo to 0.36−0.05+0.04 along with a minimal heat transfer to the night side (ϵ = 0.14−0.10+0.13). Furthermore, using five transit observations we provide stricter constraints of 3 9 ± 1 1 deg on the sky-projected obliquity of the system. Conclusions: The aligned orbit of KELT-20 b is in contrast to previous CHEOPS studies that have found strongly inclined orbits for planets orbiting other A-type stars. The comparably high planetary geometric albedo of KELT-20 b corroborates a known trend of strongly irradiated planets being more reflective. Finally, we tentatively detect signs of temporal variability in the occultation depths, which might indicate variable cloud cover advecting onto the planetary day side.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A radius valley between migrated steam worlds and evaporated rocky cores</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/09/radius-valley-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A radius valley between migrated steam worlds and evaporated rocky cores" /><published>2024-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/09/radius-valley-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/09/radius-valley-2.html"><![CDATA[<p>The radius valley (or gap) in the observed distribution of exoplanet radii, which separates smaller super-Earths from larger sub-Neptunes, is a key feature that theoretical models must explain. Conventionally, it is interpreted as the result of the loss of primordial hydrogen and helium (H/He) envelopes atop rocky cores. However, planet formation models predict that water-rich planets migrate from cold regions outside the snowline towards the star. Assuming water to be in the form of solid ice in their interior, many of these planets would be located in the radius gap contradicting observations. Here we use an advanced coupled formation and evolution model that describes the planets’ growth and evolution starting from solid, moon-sized bodies in the protoplanetary disk to mature Gyr-old planetary systems. Employing new equations of state and interior structure models to treat water as vapour mixed with H/He, we naturally reproduce the valley at the observed location. The model results demonstrate that the observed radius valley can be interpreted as the separation of less massive, rocky super-Earths formed in situ from more massive, ex situ, water-rich sub-Neptunes. Furthermore, the occurrence drop at larger radii, the so-called radius cliff, is matched by planets with water-dominated envelopes. Our statistical approach shows that the synthetic distribution of radii quantitatively agrees with observations for close-in planets, but only if low-mass planets initially containing H/He lose their atmosphere due to photoevaporation, which populates the super-Earth peak with evaporated rocky cores. Therefore, we provide a hybrid theoretical explanation of the radius gap and cliff caused by both planet formation (orbital migration) as well as evolution (atmospheric escape).</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.04380">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.04380</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="R. Burn" /><category term="C. Mordasini" /><category term="L. Mishra" /><category term="J. Haldemann" /><category term="J. Venturini" /><category term="A. Emsenhuber" /><category term="T. Henning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The radius valley (or gap) in the observed distribution of exoplanet radii, which separates smaller super-Earths from larger sub-Neptunes, is a key feature that theoretical models must explain. Conventionally, it is interpreted as the result of the loss of primordial hydrogen and helium (H/He) envelopes atop rocky cores. However, planet formation models predict that water-rich planets migrate from cold regions outside the snowline towards the star. Assuming water to be in the form of solid ice in their interior, many of these planets would be located in the radius gap contradicting observations. Here we use an advanced coupled formation and evolution model that describes the planets’ growth and evolution starting from solid, moon-sized bodies in the protoplanetary disk to mature Gyr-old planetary systems. Employing new equations of state and interior structure models to treat water as vapour mixed with H/He, we naturally reproduce the valley at the observed location. The model results demonstrate that the observed radius valley can be interpreted as the separation of less massive, rocky super-Earths formed in situ from more massive, ex situ, water-rich sub-Neptunes. Furthermore, the occurrence drop at larger radii, the so-called radius cliff, is matched by planets with water-dominated envelopes. Our statistical approach shows that the synthetic distribution of radii quantitatively agrees with observations for close-in planets, but only if low-mass planets initially containing H/He lose their atmosphere due to photoevaporation, which populates the super-Earth peak with evaporated rocky cores. Therefore, we provide a hybrid theoretical explanation of the radius gap and cliff caused by both planet formation (orbital migration) as well as evolution (atmospheric escape).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Constraining the reflective properties of WASP-178 b using CHEOPS photometry</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/08/WASP-178.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Constraining the reflective properties of WASP-178 b using CHEOPS photometry" /><published>2024-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/08/WASP-178</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/08/WASP-178.html"><![CDATA[<p>Context. Multiwavelength photometry of the secondary eclipses of extrasolar planets is able to disentangle the reflected and thermally emitted light radiated from the planetary dayside. Based on this, we can measure the planetary geometric albedo Ag, which is an indicator of the presence of clouds in the atmosphere, and the recirculation efficiency ϵ, which quantifies the energy transport within the atmosphere.
Aims: We measure Ag and ϵ for the planet WASP-178 b, a highly irradiated giant planet with an estimated equilibrium temperature of 2450 K.
Methods: We analyzed archival spectra and the light curves collected by CHEOPS and TESS to characterize the host WASP-178, refine the ephemeris of the system, and measure the eclipse depth in the passbands of the two telescopes.
Results: We measured a marginally significant eclipse depth of 70 ± 40 ppm in the TESS passband, and a statistically significant depth of 70 ± 20 ppm in the CHEOPS passband.
Conclusions: Combining the eclipse-depth measurement in the CHEOPS (λeff = 6300 Å) and TESS (λeff = 8000 Å) passbands, we constrained the dayside brightness temperature of WASP-178 b in the 2250-2800 K interval. The geometric albedo 0.1&lt; Ag&lt;0.35 generally supports the picture that giant planets are poorly reflective, while the recirculation efficiency ϵ &gt;0.7 makes WASP-178 b an interesting laboratory for testing the current heat-recirculation models.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.09037.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2309.09037.pdf</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="I. Pagano" /><category term="G. Scandariato" /><category term="V. Singh" /><category term="CHEOPS Science Team (including J.Venturini)" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Context. Multiwavelength photometry of the secondary eclipses of extrasolar planets is able to disentangle the reflected and thermally emitted light radiated from the planetary dayside. Based on this, we can measure the planetary geometric albedo Ag, which is an indicator of the presence of clouds in the atmosphere, and the recirculation efficiency ϵ, which quantifies the energy transport within the atmosphere. Aims: We measure Ag and ϵ for the planet WASP-178 b, a highly irradiated giant planet with an estimated equilibrium temperature of 2450 K. Methods: We analyzed archival spectra and the light curves collected by CHEOPS and TESS to characterize the host WASP-178, refine the ephemeris of the system, and measure the eclipse depth in the passbands of the two telescopes. Results: We measured a marginally significant eclipse depth of 70 ± 40 ppm in the TESS passband, and a statistically significant depth of 70 ± 20 ppm in the CHEOPS passband. Conclusions: Combining the eclipse-depth measurement in the CHEOPS (λeff = 6300 Å) and TESS (λeff = 8000 Å) passbands, we constrained the dayside brightness temperature of WASP-178 b in the 2250-2800 K interval. The geometric albedo 0.1&lt; Ag&lt;0.35 generally supports the picture that giant planets are poorly reflective, while the recirculation efficiency ϵ &gt;0.7 makes WASP-178 b an interesting laboratory for testing the current heat-recirculation models.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Characterising TOI-732 b and c: New insights into the M-dwarf radius and density valley</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/06/TOI-732.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Characterising TOI-732 b and c: New insights into the M-dwarf radius and density valley" /><published>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/06/TOI-732</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/02/06/TOI-732.html"><![CDATA[<p>Context. TOI-732 is an M dwarf hosting two transiting planets that are located on the two opposite sides of the radius valley. Inferring a reliable demographics for this type of systems is key to understanding their formation and evolution mechanisms.</p>

<p>Aims. By doubling the number of available space-based observations and increasing the number of radial velocity (RV) measurements, we aim at refining the parameters of TOI-732 b and c. We also use the results to study the slope of the radius valley and the density valley for a well-characterised sample of M-dwarf exoplanets.</p>

<p>Methods. We performed a global Markov chain Monte Carlo analysis by jointly modelling ground-based light curves and CHEOPS and TESS observations, along with RV time series both taken from the literature and obtained with the MAROON-X spectrograph. The slopes of the M-dwarf valleys were quantified via a support vector machine (SVM) procedure.</p>

<p>Results. TOI-732b is an ultrashort-period planet (P = 0.76837931-0.00000042+0.0000039 days) with a radius Rb = 1.325-0.058+0.057R⊕, a mass Mb = 2.46 ± 0.19 M⊕, and thus a mean density ρb = 5.8-0.8+1.0 g cm-3, while the outer planet at P = 12.252284 ± 0.000013 days has Rc = 2.39-0.11+0.10R⊕, Mc = 8.04-0.48+0.50M⊕, and thus ρc = 3.24-0.43+0.55 g cm-3. Even with respect to the most recently reported values, this work yields uncertainties on the transit depths and on the RV semi-amplitudes that are smaller up to a factor of ~1.6 and ~2.4 for TOI-732 b and c, respectively. Our calculations for the interior structure and the location of the planets in the mass-radius diagram lead us to classify TOI-732 b as a super-Earth and TOI-732 c as a mini-Neptune. Following the SVM approach, we quantified d log Rp,valley / d logP = -0.065-0.013+0.024, which is flatter than for Sun-like stars. In line with former analyses, we note that the radius valley for M-dwarf planets is more densely populated, and we further quantify the slope of the density valley as d log ρ^valley / d log P = -0.02-0.04+0.12.</p>

<p>Conclusions. Compared to FGK stars, the weaker dependence of the position of the radius valley on the orbital period might indicate that the formation shapes the radius valley around M dwarfs more strongly than the evolution mechanisms.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.12577.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.12577.pdf</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="A. Bonfanti" /><category term="M. Brady" /><category term="T. G. Wilson" /><category term="J. Venturini" /><category term="CHEOPS Science Team" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Context. TOI-732 is an M dwarf hosting two transiting planets that are located on the two opposite sides of the radius valley. Inferring a reliable demographics for this type of systems is key to understanding their formation and evolution mechanisms.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BICEPS: An improved characterization model for low- and intermediate-mass exoplanets</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/01/23/biceps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BICEPS: An improved characterization model for low- and intermediate-mass exoplanets" /><published>2024-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/01/23/biceps</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2024/01/23/biceps.html"><![CDATA[<p>Context. The number of exoplanets with precise mass and radius measurements is constantly increasing thanks to novel ground- and space-based facilities such as HARPS, ESPRESSO, CHEOPS, and TESS. The accuracy and robustness of the planetary characterization largely depends on the quality of the data, but also requires a planetary structure model, capable of accurately modeling the interior and atmospheres of exoplanets over a large range of boundary conditions.</p>

<p>Aims. Our goal is to provide an improved characterization model for planets with masses between 0.5 and 30 Earth masses, equilibrium temperatures below $&lt;2000$ K, and a wide range of planetary compositions and physical phases.</p>

<p>Methods. In this work, we present the Bayesian Interior Characterization of ExoPlanetS (BICEPS) model, which combines an adaptive Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling method with a state-of-the-art planetary structure model. BICEPS incorporates many recently developed equations of state suited for large ranges of pressures and temperatures, a description for solid and molten planetary cores and mantles, a gaseous envelope composed of hydrogen, helium, and water (with compositional gradients), and a non-gray atmospheric model.</p>

<p>Results. We find that the usage of updated equations of state has a significant impact on the interior structure prediction. The impact varies, depending on the planetary composition. For dense rocky planets, BICEPS predicts radii a few percent different to prior internal structure models. For volatile rich planets, we find differences of 10% or even larger. When applying BICEPS to a particular exoplanet, TOI-130 b, we inferred a 25% larger water mass fraction and a 15% smaller core than previous models.</p>

<p>Conclusions. The presented exoplanet characterization model is a robust method applicable over a large range of planetary masses, compositions, and thermal boundary conditions. We show the importance of implementing state-of-the-art equations of state for the encountered thermodynamic conditions of exoplanets. Hence, using BICEPS improves the predictive strength of the characterization process compared to previous methods.</p>

<hr />

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="J. Haldemann" /><category term="C. Dorn" /><category term="J. Venturini" /><category term="Y. Alibert" /><category term="W. Benz" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Context. The number of exoplanets with precise mass and radius measurements is constantly increasing thanks to novel ground- and space-based facilities such as HARPS, ESPRESSO, CHEOPS, and TESS. The accuracy and robustness of the planetary characterization largely depends on the quality of the data, but also requires a planetary structure model, capable of accurately modeling the interior and atmospheres of exoplanets over a large range of boundary conditions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A resonant sextuplet of sub-Neptunes transiting the bright star HD 110067</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/11/29/HD110067.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A resonant sextuplet of sub-Neptunes transiting the bright star HD 110067" /><published>2023-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/11/29/HD110067</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/11/29/HD110067.html"><![CDATA[<p>Planets with radii between that of the Earth and Neptune (hereafter referred to as ‘sub-Neptunes’) are found in close-in orbits around more than half of all Sun-like stars1,2. However, their composition, formation and evolution remain poorly understood3. The study of multiplanetary systems offers an opportunity to investigate the outcomes of planet formation and evolution while controlling for initial conditions and environment. Those in resonance (with their orbital periods related by a ratio of small integers) are particularly valuable because they imply a system architecture practically unchanged since its birth. Here we present the observations of six transiting planets around the bright nearby star HD 110067. We find that the planets follow a chain of resonant orbits. A dynamical study of the innermost planet triplet allowed the prediction and later confirmation of the orbits of the rest of the planets in the system. The six planets are found to be sub-Neptunes with radii ranging from 1.94R⊕ to 2.85R⊕. Three of the planets have measured masses, yielding low bulk densities that suggest the presence of large hydrogen-dominated atmospheres.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.17775.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.17775.pdf</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="R. Luque" /><category term="H. P. Osborn" /><category term="A. Leleu" /><category term="CHEOPS Science Team (including J.Venturini)" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Planets with radii between that of the Earth and Neptune (hereafter referred to as ‘sub-Neptunes’) are found in close-in orbits around more than half of all Sun-like stars1,2. However, their composition, formation and evolution remain poorly understood3. The study of multiplanetary systems offers an opportunity to investigate the outcomes of planet formation and evolution while controlling for initial conditions and environment. Those in resonance (with their orbital periods related by a ratio of small integers) are particularly valuable because they imply a system architecture practically unchanged since its birth. Here we present the observations of six transiting planets around the bright nearby star HD 110067. We find that the planets follow a chain of resonant orbits. A dynamical study of the innermost planet triplet allowed the prediction and later confirmation of the orbits of the rest of the planets in the system. The six planets are found to be sub-Neptunes with radii ranging from 1.94R⊕ to 2.85R⊕. Three of the planets have measured masses, yielding low bulk densities that suggest the presence of large hydrogen-dominated atmospheres.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Refining the properties of the TOI-178 system with CHEOPS and TESS</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/08/23/TOI-178.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Refining the properties of the TOI-178 system with CHEOPS and TESS" /><published>2023-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/08/23/TOI-178</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/08/23/TOI-178.html"><![CDATA[<p>Context. The TOI-178 system consists of a nearby late K-dwarf transited by six planets in the super-Earth to mini-Neptune regime, with radii
ranging from ∼1.1 to 2.9 R⊕ and orbital periods between 1.9 and 20.7 days. All planets but the innermost one form a chain of Laplace resonances.
Mass estimates derived from a preliminary radial velocity (RV) dataset suggest that the planetary densities do not decrease in a monotonic way
with the orbital distance to the star, contrary to what one would expect based on simple formation and evolution models.
Aims. To improve the characterisation of this key system and prepare for future studies (in particular with JWST), we perform a detailed photo-
metric study based on 40 new CHEOPS visits, one new TESS sector, as well as previously published CHEOPS, TESS, and NGTS data.
Methods. First we update the parameters of the host star using the new parallax from Gaia EDR3. We then perform a global analysis of the 100
transits contained in our data to refine the physical and orbital parameters of the six planets and study their transit timing variations (TTVs). We
also use our extensive dataset to place constraints on the radii and orbital periods of potential additional transiting planets in the system.
Results. Our analysis significantly refines the transit parameters of the six planets, most notably their radii, for which we now obtain relative
precisions ≲3%, with the exception of the smallest planet b for which the precision is 5.1%. Combined with the RV mass estimates, the measured
TTVs allow us to constrain the eccentricities of planets c to g, which are found to be all below 0.02, as expected from stability requirements. Taken
alone, the TTVs also suggest a higher mass for planet d than the one estimated from the RVs, which had been found to yield a surprisingly low
density for this planet. However, the masses derived from the current TTV dataset are very prior-dependent and further observations, over a longer temporal baseline, are needed to deepen our understanding of this iconic planetary system.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.11394.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.11394.pdf</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="L. Delrez" /><category term="A. Leleu" /><category term="A. Brandeker" /><category term="CHEOPS Science Team (including J.Venturini)" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Context. The TOI-178 system consists of a nearby late K-dwarf transited by six planets in the super-Earth to mini-Neptune regime, with radii ranging from ∼1.1 to 2.9 R⊕ and orbital periods between 1.9 and 20.7 days. All planets but the innermost one form a chain of Laplace resonances. Mass estimates derived from a preliminary radial velocity (RV) dataset suggest that the planetary densities do not decrease in a monotonic way with the orbital distance to the star, contrary to what one would expect based on simple formation and evolution models. Aims. To improve the characterisation of this key system and prepare for future studies (in particular with JWST), we perform a detailed photo- metric study based on 40 new CHEOPS visits, one new TESS sector, as well as previously published CHEOPS, TESS, and NGTS data. Methods. First we update the parameters of the host star using the new parallax from Gaia EDR3. We then perform a global analysis of the 100 transits contained in our data to refine the physical and orbital parameters of the six planets and study their transit timing variations (TTVs). We also use our extensive dataset to place constraints on the radii and orbital periods of potential additional transiting planets in the system. Results. Our analysis significantly refines the transit parameters of the six planets, most notably their radii, for which we now obtain relative precisions ≲3%, with the exception of the smallest planet b for which the precision is 5.1%. Combined with the RV mass estimates, the measured TTVs allow us to constrain the eccentricities of planets c to g, which are found to be all below 0.02, as expected from stability requirements. Taken alone, the TTVs also suggest a higher mass for planet d than the one estimated from the RVs, which had been found to yield a surprisingly low density for this planet. However, the masses derived from the current TTV dataset are very prior-dependent and further observations, over a longer temporal baseline, are needed to deepen our understanding of this iconic planetary system.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Investigating the visible phase-curve variability of 55 Cnc e</title><link href="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/07/27/55Cnc-e.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Investigating the visible phase-curve variability of 55 Cnc e" /><published>2023-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/07/27/55Cnc-e</id><content type="html" xml:base="juliaventurini.com/co-author/2023/07/27/55Cnc-e.html"><![CDATA[<p>55 Cnc e is an ultra-short period super-Earth transiting a Sun-like star. Previous observations in the optical range detected a time-variable flux modulation that is phased with the planetary orbital period, whose amplitude is too large to be explained by reflected light and thermal emission alone. The goal of the study is to investigate the origin of the variability and timescale of the phase-curve modulation in 55 Cnc e. To this end, we used the CHaracterising ExOPlanet Satellite (CHEOPS), whose exquisite photometric precision provides an opportunity to characterise minute changes in the phase curve from one orbit to the next. CHEOPS observed 29 individual visits of 55 Cnc e between March 2020 and February 2022. Based on these observations, we investigated the different processes that could be at the origin of the observed modulation. In particular, we built a toy model to assess whether a circumstellar torus of dust driven by radiation pressure and gravity might match the observed flux variability timescale. We find that the phase-curve amplitude and peak offset of 55 Cnc e do vary between visits. The sublimation timescales of selected dust species reveal that silicates expected in an Earth-like mantle would not survive long enough to explain the observed phase-curve modulation. We find that silicon carbide, quartz, and graphite are plausible candidates for the circumstellar torus composition because their sublimation timescales are long. The extensive CHEOPS observations confirm that the phase-curve amplitude and offset vary in time.We find that dust could provide the grey opacity source required to match the observations. However, the data at hand do not provide evidence that circumstellar material with a variable grain mass per unit area causes the observed variability. Future observations with the James Webb Space Telescope promise exciting insights into this iconic super-Earth.</p>

<hr />

<p>Arxiv-link: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06085">https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06085</a></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Julia Venturini</name></author><category term="Co-Author" /><category term="E. A. Meier Valdés" /><category term="B. M. Morris" /><category term="B.-O. Demory" /><category term="CHEOPS Science Team (including J.Venturini)" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[55 Cnc e is an ultra-short period super-Earth transiting a Sun-like star. Previous observations in the optical range detected a time-variable flux modulation that is phased with the planetary orbital period, whose amplitude is too large to be explained by reflected light and thermal emission alone. The goal of the study is to investigate the origin of the variability and timescale of the phase-curve modulation in 55 Cnc e. To this end, we used the CHaracterising ExOPlanet Satellite (CHEOPS), whose exquisite photometric precision provides an opportunity to characterise minute changes in the phase curve from one orbit to the next. CHEOPS observed 29 individual visits of 55 Cnc e between March 2020 and February 2022. Based on these observations, we investigated the different processes that could be at the origin of the observed modulation. In particular, we built a toy model to assess whether a circumstellar torus of dust driven by radiation pressure and gravity might match the observed flux variability timescale. We find that the phase-curve amplitude and peak offset of 55 Cnc e do vary between visits. The sublimation timescales of selected dust species reveal that silicates expected in an Earth-like mantle would not survive long enough to explain the observed phase-curve modulation. We find that silicon carbide, quartz, and graphite are plausible candidates for the circumstellar torus composition because their sublimation timescales are long. The extensive CHEOPS observations confirm that the phase-curve amplitude and offset vary in time.We find that dust could provide the grey opacity source required to match the observations. However, the data at hand do not provide evidence that circumstellar material with a variable grain mass per unit area causes the observed variability. Future observations with the James Webb Space Telescope promise exciting insights into this iconic super-Earth.]]></summary></entry></feed>